I'm Sarah Sharp, a deal attorney who
helps people buy and sell businesses
every day, mainly accounting practices.
And I am in the midst of my biggest deal
season. So, biggest deal season ever and
busiest part of the year for me
normally. And on top of all of that, I
had three deals die this week. So, I'm
going to tell you the three things that
kill deals even after you've drafted the
purchase agreement. Kind of on the 50ard
line, right? And that was the case with
all three of these deals that died this
week. And it's very rare for me to have
any deal die after a purchase agreement.
So I'm reflecting on how it could be
avoided and why it happened. So the
first thing that kills deals of the
three, the first thing that kills deals
after you've drafted the purchase
agreements and you've gone through
diligence is pretty simple and
unfortunately pretty unavoidable. And
that is something new happens, right? So
whether that's somebody being sued or
somebody having a data breach or a key
employee quitting, that kind of thing
can come up at any time. And when it
happens, it doesn't matter if you've run
the most clean, perfect deal ever. It's
still probably the right time to walk
away if you're the buyer. And if you're
the seller, unfortunately, it's going to
be hard to convince somebody to move
forward with you, right? So, it's not
always that the thing is of an enormous
magnitude, per se. It's often simply
that I'm cleaning out a drawer while I
do this. It's often simply that it's
happening during the same time as the
deal and the parties are just not going
to have enough information quickly
enough to be to know if it's a big deal
or not. Like with a data breach, you
might have a data breach that's
ultimately very finite and it's not like
huge. Nothing giant happens from it.
there's just a couple affected parties,
everybody's notified, the data breach is
incredibly minimal and that kind of
thing. But when you first learn about
it, you don't know. You haven't done the
you haven't had a chance to see if
something bigger is going to come out of
it. And the same with a lawsuit. It
might get settled very quickly, but
there's just no understanding of how big
the liability will be and it's probably
not going to be something that gets
resolved quickly enough for the deal to
go through. So something completely
unavoidable, surprising comes up. So,
that is a good reason for a deal to die.
And usually if a deal dies for those
reasons, it's partially at least because
they had a provision in your purchase
agreement and they made the person
promise that those things aren't true.
Because what you don't want is to not
have a reason for the seller to tell you
about those new bad outcomes. Right? So,
our purchase agreements always say, you
know, I promise I'm not being sued.
Article three reps, right? I promise I'm
not being sued. I haven't been sued. I
promise I don't have any employment
claims. I haven't had any, you know, if
they do, they explain what they were. I
promise I don't have any security
breaches. That kind of thing. So, if
you've got those promises, then all of a
sudden you're asking the seller to sign,
they're going to really hesitate when
all of a sudden that happens. And in all
of the cases where I've had that happen,
that is what susted it out. It wasn't
the seller that wanted to disclose the
new thing. It was the fact that they
were going to have to sign the purchase
agreement that promised that thing
wasn't true that made it come up. So,
you know, say what you will about a deal
that doesn't make it all the way through
to closing. And I know it's not a good
outcome for anyone to have paid a lawyer
to prepare all of the documents, but
sometimes just that process is really
helpful because by virtue of having
those reps and warranties and having the
seller look at them with their lawyer,
that pushes them over the edge of
disclosing something to you, the buyer,
that is really important to know and
that they probably should have
disclosed, but they weren't totally sure
they wanted to. So, you know, while that
is a failure in some ways because the
deal doesn't go through, the refrain you
will hear me say in this video many
times is sometimes the best deal is no
deal. And if there's some huge data
breach that you don't have the ability
to get your arms around or if there's
some lawsuit that's going to take who
knows how long to resolve, you know,
that's probably not the right deal to do
then. And maybe it will be later, but
it's it's not your opportunity. And the
best deal in that instance is probably
no deal. So that is the first. The
second thing that can kill deals is over
lawyering. You could argue under
lawyering, but lawyers, lawyers, there's
a reason that they call us deal killers.
We probably get too much blame lawyers
do for killing deals because I mean I
regularly tell clients that they can
blame me for pulling out of a deal.
Also, you know, some deal like you're
most likely to talk to your lawyer if
you're planning on pulling out of a
deal. So maybe they're going to be the
ones that get blamed because they were
the last ones to talk to you and they're
going to help you understand your risk.
So of course we're going to be there.
Doctors aren't murderers. Um even if
they're there when there's a lot of
death, right? So we're we're certainly
not always to blame, but sometimes we
are. And in particular this week, I had
a lot of lawyers who seem to be trying
their darnest to kill deals. Folks who
don't have a lot of experience in the
industry can certainly do it. There, in
this case, I had a lot of parallel deals
where there's a lot of over lawyering,
meaning 89page purchase agreements for a
$300,000
firm acquisition. You know, it's just
overdone and it's intimidating. And
ultimately in this case, the lawyers
took a really hard stance on things that
didn't fit the overall profile of the
deal. Like not just the money, right?
But the So there can be zero dollar
deals. Any deal attorney, any M&A
attorney has done Z deals on hundreds
and hundreds of pages of transaction
agreements where that was appropriate
because the risk was so big. It it can
be either the the purchase price is big
or the risk is so enormous, the
liability profile is so enormous that it
justifies having that kind of um legal
team and legal diligence. Unfortunately,
bad advice from lawyers can be or lack
of good advice. For instance, um a lot
of times clients will come to me and we
will have a long discussion about
something that they want me to do. And
sometimes I will say no and I like I I
don't think that that's right and I'm
not, you know, I don't think I'm the
right lawyer for this. So I understand
if you want to do it and that's a deal
point, but I'm not going to be the one
to do it. Very rarely do I say that, but
on occasion I've definitely said that.
Some lawyers have never ever said that.
And some lawyers that I've worked with
both like you know on the same side
don't view their job as inclusive of
business judgment calls at all. So they
won't weigh in. So they might have a
purchase agreement. They may have
negotiated the entire profile of the
terms. All of the parties have agreed on
something and their client comes in and
says, "You know what? I want to change
the purchase price and reduce it by a
million dollars." And whereas I and many
of my colleagues would go, "Whoa, are
you sure you want to do that? that might
cause them to walk away. That is a
significant and material retrade that's
going to be poorly received. Let's talk
about it. Some lawyers will just go,
"Okay," and do it. The deal blows up,
right? So, it can be really valuable to
have lawyers, especially ones who will
kind of make sure that you're staying
generally within the bumpers of what is
considered market for terms. If you're
trying to pull a, you know, kill a deal
because you absolutely refuse as the
seller to be on the hook for anything
postclosing and you're saying no
indignification, no survival
requirements. I'm not going to
personally sign anything. It's all going
to be on behalf of the company, the
company that I'm about to dissolve after
I sell these assets. That's not a very
reasonable position to take and a lot of
people are not going to want to do that
deal. If you have a lawyer who's not
telling you that, that can end it. So
over lawyering certainly having someone
just run to death over every tiny little
feature of a deal. Someone who's wanting
you to call the company that the copier
leases through to make sure that they
can assign the lease at closing.
Somebody who wants every single te
crossed and lowercase J dotted can kill
a deal just by wearing the parties out.
Because in my world, which is small
business, most of the sellers are also
running a business and they just don't
have the bandwidth to do all of those
things. So, if you have too big of a
firm expecting too much, expecting the
type of response from the other side
that you would get if you had a deal
team instead of just the owner doing it,
that can kill it. That can absolutely
kill it. The third thing in the three
things that can kill a deal right before
closing is just complete honest
disagreement on the terms. And as much
as I try to get everything agreed upon
in the letter of intent, and if you've
watched any of my videos, I'm sure
you've seen me say that, I want the
parties to put all, you know, in a term
sheet or a letter of intent everything
that they can about what they agree to.
On very rare occasion, even still doing
that, the parties draft the purchase
agreements, and it's only in the
negotiation of those agreements, do we
finally realize that there's just a
disagreement about a material term. So
usually when that happens with me, I've
put everything I can in the LOI prior to
the deal getting very far. So usually we
know if we don't have alignment on the
terms, but so if there is a subsequent
just good faith non-alignment on terms,
it's usually something that's let's say
kind of not something you would put in a
term sheet or an LOI. So it's more of a
subsequent type of class B terms. So,
some really legal ease type of things,
governing law, indomnification. I even
put indignification cap and survival
stuff in my uh letters of intent. But
sometimes people come to me and they've
already executed a letter of intent and
so that hasn't been decided upon yet.
So, you know, usually when something
goes all the way through being drafted
and ultimately falls apart, it is
something that is in the legal realm
like indomnification, survival, personal
guarantee, collateral, that kind of
thing. They they just didn't have any
reason to talk about earlier. And that
it's hard to avoid. Unfortunately, some
people, you know, you can say this is
market, this isn't market. You can have
two lawyers on a call like I was on
earlier that said, "I have done a blah
blah blah millions of these deals and
I've never and the other one says me,
well, I've done blah blah blah blah
these deals and I've never like who
cares if ultimately the parties just
don't agree to a term and they can't
allocate the liability. If the buyer is
just not willing to personally guarantee
the note and they never talked about it
before. If the seller's just not willing
to personally represent the status of
the business is good and in good shape
and they've never talked about it before
until you're deep on a call with a bunch
of lawyers going through the agreements.
That's just one of those things that
unfortunately sometimes happens. You
can't touch every single point in the
letter of intent and unfortunately like
happened today. Even if you do, the
parties can change their minds. So,
those are the three main ways that I see
uh deals die, unfortunately, before
closing, but after you've drafted the
transaction documents. Um, we do
everything we can to avoid them. Check
out dealacademy.org or for more ways to
avoid killing a deal.